Guide to the Arthur H. Landis Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.066
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Arthur H. Landis Photographs
1917-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Landis, Arthur H., 1917-1986
ALBA.PHOTO.066
1.75 Linear Feet
Arthur H. Landis (1917-1986) joined the 15th International Brigade in 1937 and fought with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion. In 1967, Landis wrote The Abraham Lincoln Brigade about Americans in the Spanish Civil War, and later published Spain! The Unfinished Revolution, about the political complexities of the war. The collection contains photographs from Landis' scrapbook and his mother Alice Fries' photo albums, including images of his childhood and family. Alice Fries was a singer, dancer and member of the American Guild of Variety Artists. Images from the Spanish Civil War include bombed buildings, Ernie Parlor and unidentified international volunteers, medical personnel and vehicles, and Spanish soldiers. There are additional photographs of demonstrations in the United States attended by the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. The collection includes color slides of Spanish cities: Albacete, Belchite, Brunete, Murcia, and Teruel, and maps of various Republican fronts. Many images depict Landis' daily life in Hermosa Beach and Los Angeles, California.
(4 boxes) Approximately 700 black and white photographs sized from 1 x 1 inch to 10 x 13 inches, 58 35mm color slides, and 47 black and white negatives sized from 1 ½ x 1 inches to 4 x 5 inches.
Provenance
The Arthur H. Landis Photograph Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Arthur H. Landis in the early 1990s. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The images in the Landis Photograph Collection were separated from the Landis manuscript collection at the time of processing.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Arthur H. Landis was born into a family of vaudeville performers in Birmingham, Alabama in 1917, and spent most of his youth in Redondo Beach, California. Landis joined the 15th International Brigade in 1937 and fought with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion. He worked as a scout, a typographer, and an artillery spotter with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion, and fought in the battles of Aragon and Teruel, where he was injured. Landis also worked for a stint for an intelligence unit, and participated in an aborted operation to blow up the Italian Fleet headquarters. Just before Barcelona fell to Franco, Landis helped load the 15th Brigade Archives onto a Soviet ship. He sailed back to the U.S. on the R.M.S. Ausonia in December 1938. For further biographical information on Landis, and to review the scope and contents of his manuscript collection see, Guide to the Arthur H. Landis Papers, ALBA 66 [Note: hotlink].
Landis' mother Alice Fries traveled to small towns across the Midwest and West working variety shows—including the Nut Chorus and Ralston Chorus—as a singer and dancer. Fries became Alice Landis when she married William N. Landis, Arthur's father. William, also a performer, entered the army in 1920. By 1922 the couple was estranged. Alice married her stage partner, Richard Yaryan, and changed her name to Alice Yaryan. The duo performed under the stage name fast-Stepping Man and Maid. In the late 1930s Alice sometimes used Alice Harper as a stage name (her father's name was Harper) when she performed in the duo Harper & King. Fries was a member of the American Guild of Variety Artists.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Photographs. The Landis Photographic Collection consists predominantly of photographs from Landis' scrapbooks and the personal photo albums of his mother, Alice Fries. These items contained images of Landis' childhood and family: grandmother Ethel Fries, father William (Bill) N. Landis, and brother William (Billie) H. Landis. Other family members represented in the series include Landis' aunts Edith and Mabel Fries, cousins Grace Fries and Helen Fries-Topping, uncle Jim Topping, and nephew William D. Landis.
Landis' scrapbooks were disassembled and the photographs divided according to subject category. Photocopies of the original order of Landis' photo albums are contained in Box 4, Folders 9-12. Loose photographs from Alice Fries' keepsake albums were removed and added to the photograph collection, arranged according to subject category. Her albums that contained only photographs were preserved intact. Photocopies indicating the original order of the disassembled albums are in Box 4, Folders 7-8.
Images from the Spanish Civil War include, bombed buildings, Arthur Landis, Ernie Parlor and unidentified international volunteers, medical personnel and vehicles, and Spanish soldiers. There are additional photographs of political demonstrations and rallies in the United States attended by the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade including one image of Dolores Ibárruri in Spain and one image of Paul Robeson, Morris Fishman, and Bart van der Schelling singing at a gathering in Los Angeles, California.
Series II: Slides. Most of the 53 slides of Spanish cities, rivers and other sites of combat were taken by Jack Levine, following AL's instructions, in Spain in June and October 1966. The collection contains two slides of the Valley of the Fallen, a memorial to the dead of the Spanish Civil War, where only General Francisco Franco and José Antonio Primo de Rivera, founder of the Falange, were commemorated by name. The series also contains five images of maps depicting Republican fronts credited to the California State College at Los Angeles. AL used the slides in a presentation to veterans and friends in Los Angeles.
Series III: Negatives. The negatives are contained in a separate box from the photographs and slides. The 47 images in this series are mostly of Landis' Hermosa Beach home and neighborhood. There is also one image of Landis as a child, one image of Landis with his brother and one image of Landis in Spain during the Civil War. The series also contains images of maps depicting Republican fronts during the Spanish Civil War and two images of Dolores Ibárruri at a veterans' event in Spain. The negative of Landis in Spain matches the print in Box 2, Folder 16. One of the negatives of Dolores Ibárruri matches the print in Box 2, Folder 5 .The remaining negatives do not match any prints.
Series IV: Photocopied Photo Albums and Scrapbooks. These photocopies display the original order of the Arthur Landis' and Alice Fries' photo albums and scrapbooks prior to disassembling.
Arrangement
Folders arranged alphabetically by topic.
The files are grouped into 4 series:
Missing Title
I. Photographs
II. Slides
III. Negatives
IV. Photocopied Photo Albums and Scrapbooks
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Arthur H. Landis Audiotape Collection, ALBA Audio 66
Arthur H. Landis Manuscript Collection, ALBA 66
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Negatives (photographic); Black-and-white photographs.; Murcia (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Biography; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Belchite (Spain); Brunete (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Valencia (Spain); Toledo (Spain); Madrid (Spain); Albacete (Spain); Slides (photographs); Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Vaudeville |z Middle West.; Vaudeville |z United States |y 20th century.; Vaudeville |z United States |x Songs and music.; Teruel (Spain); Fuentes de Ebro (Spain); Vaudeville |z California |x History |y 20th century.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Archives; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Historical Commission; Fishman, Mosess (Moe), 1916-2007; Fries, Alice; Hutchins, Evelyn, 1910-1982; Ibárruri, Dolores, 1895-1989; Landis, Arthur H., 1917-1986; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Rahman, Evelyn.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; American Guild of Variety Artists; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Photographs
  - Baseball Game, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Building/Construction Site, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dance (VALB), Los Angeles: Bart van der Schelling, Paul Robeson, Morris Fishman, Arthur Landis, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Demonstrations and Rallies, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Demonstrations and Rallies: National Maritime Union (Milwaukee), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Demonstrations and Rallies: Vietnam War, undated, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fries, Alice (see also Landis, Alice), 1910s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fries, Alice: Childhood/Youth, 1910s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fries, Alice: Family, 1910s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fries, Alice: Friends, 1910s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fries, Alice: Matted Photographs, ca.1920s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fries, Alice: Photo Album (I), 1911-1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fries, Alice: Photo Album (II), 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fries, Alice: Photo Album (III), 1920-1922 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fries, Alice: Theatrical Photographs, 1910s-1930s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hermosa Harbor/Los Angeles, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - High School Yearbook (photos), 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hutchins, Evelyn, undated, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Brigade: Veterans Events, post-Civil War (includes images of Dolores Ibárruri), undated, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Landis, Alice (see also Fries, Alice), 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Portrait, 1925 (Box Shared Tamiment 044, Folder 6)
  - Landis, Arthur, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Landis, Arthur: Childhood/Youth, 1920s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Landis, Arthur: Family and Friends (from Photo Albums and Scrapbook), 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Landis, Arthur: In Hospital (United States), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Landis, Arthur: In Los Angeles (photographed by Wendell Hamick; humorous captions by AL), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Landis, Arthur: Spanish Civil War, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Landis, William N., undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Parlor, Ernie: Spanish Civil War, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Spanish Civil War: Bombed Buildings, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Spanish Civil War: Combat, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Spanish Civil War: International Brigade, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Spanish Civil War: Medical Personnel, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Spanish Civil War: Miscellaneous, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Spanish Civil War: Spanish Soldiers, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Spanish Civil War: Unidentified Soldiers, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Travel: Alaska, Hawaii, San Francisco, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified Prints: Individuals and Groups, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Vaudeville Performers, 1920s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - World War II (Airplane Crew, non-combat), 1940s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Yaryan, Richard, 1920s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Yaryan, Richard: with Alice Fries, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Series II: Slides
  - Albacete, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Belchite, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Brunete, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Fuentes de Ebro, Jun 1966 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Madrid, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Maps, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Murcia, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Rio Guadarrama, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Rio Jarama, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - San Martin de la Vega, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Tarazona de la Mancha, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Teruel, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Toledo, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Valencia, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Valley of the Fallen, Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Villanueva de la Cañada, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Series III: Negatives
  - Artwork, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hermosa Harbor/Los Angeles, Nov 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Landis, Arthur: Childhood, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Landis, Arthur: Spanish Civil War, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Spanish Civil War: Maps, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Veterans Events: Post Civil War, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Photocopied Photo Albums and Scrapbooks
  - Fries, Alice: Photo Album I, 1911-1915 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fries, Alice: Photo Album III, 1920-1922 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Landis, Arthur: Scrapbook I, 1910s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Landis, Arthur: Scrapbook II, 1910s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Landis, Arthur: Scrapbook III, 1930s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Landis, Arthur: Scrapbook IV, 1910s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 12)